so we were describing shinjang which is
uh an added feature to the ninth level
which makes you feel as if you had sunk
into the object and
um if you have level nine with
shinjang uh it will become sham it will
become the Deep state of meditation that
you need to see emptiness directly
[Music]
he
says he says uh when you get this
feeling of mental and physical Bliss in
a deep state of meditation when your
body feels light and strong as if it's
going to float off uh by the way at this
point your back is straight all the time
like West Point guy something you know
it's just you can't help it you're
always sitting on the edge of the chair
is it 4 in or something and and you're
always your back is completely straight
and it's just automatic and it feels
great uh it's just a
physical ecstasy from that and then uh
he
says says it could get out of head all
right like don't get caught up in the
good feeling of it right he
says let it let it go a little bit don't
don't like get all uh lost in the good
feeling like let that go let the Bliss
go a little
bit and then it will feel like someone
tuned down the Bliss slightly
okay then go into like a standard
ecstasy and uh
and and stay one pointedly on the object
your
[Music]
meditation then you will have
ai okay
sham and as we said this afternoon
there's an there's an entire Spectrum
like the spectrum of light if you've
ever studied the light
spectrum uh there's a huge spectrum of
meditational states and you can think of
them as small stripes on a very long
ruler what do you call yard stick and
and there are tiny tiny stripes on the
yard stck of different colors and what
we want to do is get up past level 9
push it a little bit further into
physical and mental ecstasy and stay
there and park the mind there and don't
go higher okay there are higher States
you don't go higher stay there you're
out of this realm all right you're out
of the current realm you're not in this
world anymore your mind is out you're
into a a meditation so deep that if you
passed away at that moment you would you
would actually go to another
real you're not at all
aware of if
someone banged a what do you call a Gong
in your ear you wouldn't hear anything
if someone wave McDonald's french fries
in front of your nose you wouldn't smell
them right you
arear right you are withdrawn from your
sense objects completely sense
sensus uh totally immersed in in deep
meditation and it physically if you get
there this is just a personal advice
okay if you get it's not in the T if you
get there you feel as if you are rising
uh you feel like you're in a you are
physically rising to a different realm
okay and that's
called
means
here here refers to the form
okay a
place a paradisical place you would go
if you died at that moment okay so the
meditation itself is called form Realm
or di meditation but it doesn't mean
you're in the former okay it means that
if you died at that moment that
meditation would throw you into a higher
Paradise realm okay temporary realm not
a good place to go
permanently
uh near means you don't even get to the
first of the form realm levels there are
four form realm
meditations near means you don't even
get to the real first one all right the
first job ribe gave me when I met him in
[Music]
1974 he gave me a text to he wor he told
me you're going to work on this text to
translate it's called
abidos it was a translation it was the
commentary by the first D lover I spent
12 years on that text okay in the first
year I had no idea what anything was
about you know like he would explain the
words to me me and they would be saying
there's a form realm there's four levels
to the form realm you're not even
getting to level one you are in the
preliminary level to stage one of the
form real you know and it all meant
nothing to me you know so I don't know
what the four formal meditations are I
don't know what they feel like and I
could therefore I could hardly matter to
me whether I'm in the preliminary part
of the first one or the or the main what
they call Main stage musi me main stage
near do means to pinate part but the all
the whole book for a year was about
things which I couldn't have any
experience of at all you know and it was
very frustrating you know then we got to
the third chapter and they started
talking about how the sun was created
and then I felt comfortable you know but
the whole first section it was all about
stuff that I couldn't relate to at all
cuz I this just they are making
distinctions between things that I I I
have no experience of it all so anyway
that's how it's going to be for you
there's uh four for real levels
meditations uh at this point when you've
just got this Ecstasy of body and
mind you haven't even gotten to the
first form you are at the preliminary
they call the preliminary stage before
the main stage of the first format
you're in a
tiny slot
a bar if you've seen what they call
those things that measure the
Spectrum spectrometer yeah we had to use
them in gamology school you have a
spectrometer spectrometer and they have
all these lines right of different color
uh you are in one tiny section of the
entire spectrum of meditation called the
preliminary to the first form realm
level meditation it's called m
say it's a double negative me means not
me means isn't sorry me means isn't May
mean it isn't
it's you don't okay you don't it's not
all right what's that mean choke choke
means to have time to do something me
choke means I don't have time to do
something me CH man means I don't not
have time to do anything all right it's
not that I don't have time to do
anything all right the level of
meditation has a very specific name
called it's not that I don't have time
all right
me only in that slight sliver of the
entire range of thousands of meditations
and meditation objects can you see
emptiness th only from that platform can
you see emptiness directly right only
from that platform that specific
platform can you ever get the Mind still
enough but not over still to see
emptiness directly if you see emptiness
directly then within a short time you
can change the planet you can change the
entire planet you can stop the pain of
entire planets right you have that power
if if you just get to that meditation so
what we're talking about this whole
week's uh class on meditation has
nothing to do with the actual goal right
the goal is to use that
meditation to to see a certain object
you cannot see Ultimate Reality unless
you can get to this particular level of
meditation you have to you must right uh
and that's the point of studying all the
11 levels and the five problems and
eight anal and six powers and the four
states of mind okay uh that's the reason
to do a retreat it's only for that
that's the only
goal if you see it directly for 20
minutes you will have the power to
transform the entire planet right it's
beautiful it's very beautiful that's
that's what you really want to do okay
what are the most popular movies around
Spider-Man Iron Man
Transformers Batman Batman Returns you
know I
it's people who s it's people who saved
the world right uh it's people who saved
the world why do they keep making movies
about people who save the
world because that's what you really
want to do with your life okay like okay
you want to eat you want to have a
house uh you want to sleep you want to
have sex you you want to have a job you
want money those are all true everybody
would like those things but deep deep
down inside and the reason why people
are so often unhappy is that you want to
save the world you want to you want to
make this world a better place that's
your that's your deepest fantasy and
that's what keeps you vo okay in your in
the back of your mind you know it's
useless to collect money because you
will just lose it all you know it's
useless to eat because you can only eat
so much right uh in the and you know
that death is coming and so in the back
of your heart you know the only
meaningful thing to do would be to
change the world help the
world if you get to this stage of
meditation you can do it a single person
can transform the world has the power to
transform the world if you can reach
this state of meditation and see this
okay so what would be the natural place
to go now in our
discussion mean we just reached
[Music]
that level what do you want to talk
about
now what are you going to focus that
state of mind now you see you could
focus it on baseball or oranges or you
know anything it's just a tool you could
focus it on anything yes maam
oh yeah good okay it's a good question
she said there must have been people who
studied these books got these teachings
did these kinds of meditations and why
do we still see the world having pain
right why are there still Wars and
like were you here for the pen
thing did you did you see when we talked
about the pen no oh
okay so the the human being saw the pen
as
a pen and the Dog Saw the pen as
a something to chew right so uh one
level of being one level of being saw
something to chew on another level of
being saw a pen maybe there's a third
level of being who could see a pen and
they don't even think of it as a pen
they they think of it as something to
change the world or save the world to
them it looks like a an instrument for
saving a world I could write something
and save a world with this you
[Music]
see
so today in this room for example it's
possible that there are those kinds of
people who saw emptiness that way okay
and they see the
world as a pen and we see it as a
dog toy okay so it's the same it's the
same in their
world uh hunger has been stopped and War
has been stopped they don't see
Iraq that we see they don't see the
Afghanistan that we see they don't see
people hungry in Africa that we see okay
we're in the same world and we see
different things
uh the dog and the human are in the same
room but there's two realities in the
room
okay
so they see the world differently but to
save the world they have to get us to
see the world differently right
okay and for
a for a dog who graduated to being a
human
can you imagine how difficult it is for
them to convince the other dogs that the
pen is a
pen you see you imagine how much work it
would take for a super dog to talk to
the other dogs and say look you could
use this thing in another way you know
this is not just
a a chw toy you can do other things with
this but it would take years of patient
work for the dog who figured out the pen
to explain it to the other dogs it would
take a lot of work many years of work to
to explain it because the other dogs
never experienced it you see
okay that's sh when you reach that level
that's shamata and now you can towards
EMP this is the only book I've ever seen
an explanation of the name of the level
the level is
called in
England it's not that I don't have
time it's not that I don't have time
like why why do they call the level that
why is it called that he said
this state of meditation is a is
something which you cannot do
without if you hope to gain uh infinite
numbers of realizations which are both
of this world and Beyond this world okay
so there are there are realizations of
this world and there are realizations
Beyond this world and you can't get to
them unless you have this state of mind
so he says therefore we call it which
would mean I don't have I don't have
time not to try to get this all right I
don't
have it's not that I don't have time to
try to develop this meditation that's
why he you need it
I admit says that if you kept working on
your meditation you could go through the
four form realm meditations and you
could go through the four formless realm
meditations which are just even deeper
states of
meditation they are more calm more
focused than the other ones right I
admit that you could do it but
but there wouldn't be any point to it
right just to get deeper into meditation
there's no higher goal than to see
emptiness directly there's no reason to
go higher in the in the form and
formless realm
meditations why do they exist
uh yeah they weren't they weren't
designed uh by
anybody uh they just are there if you
reach them you get born in
more uh temporary happiness so they're
actually
considered an
obstacle but while they're there it's
just if if you go deeper you can get a
higher
Reaper there's a weird thing about these
meditations all
right the the higher ones than the one
you need to see emptiness right the four
form realm and the four formless realm
meditations there's a weird thing about
them uh as you move up through those
eight uh the Mind becomes more and more
subtle all right
so is a cup of coffee made with three
scoops of coffee and two spoons of sugar
is it strong or
not no you can say it depends right it's
strong compared to T it's not strong
compared to coffee made with five scoops
of coffee all right uh so what happens
as you move up through these eight is
that let's say if you're watching your
breath
uh it gets quieter and quieter and
quieter and quieter you start out I said
it the other day right you start out
where you can block out the noise of the
traffic
outside and then it seems subtle to not
have noise of
traffic then you block out the noise of
people sniffing in the room slurping
what do they do it's a meditation demon
they
go in the middle of meditation you know
in 100 people everyone's silent for 10
minutes and then somebody goes you know
just let it drip okay it won't hurt you
uh anyway then that becomes subtle right
then people
stop and then it's all silent and
suddenly you can hear the you can hear
your breath moving through the hairs of
your nose it's a slight whistling sound
okay like he goes
[Music]
really now if you get subtle if you get
quiet enough it becomes quite uh
noticeable right then you like go deeper
and then all you can hear is this
uh What's happen that's your heartbeat
then your heartbeat gets really loud it
becomes a it becomes like somebody's
banging a drum in your ear
like and then you get past that you go
deeper and then you can hear
[Music]
this what's
that it's a air hitting the eardrums you
can hear discret molecules of air
hitting your
[Music]
earr like that
okay as you
move deeper into meditation as you go
one step deeper from the traffic noise
down to the molecules hitting your ear
drum your mind gets more calm and less
likely to get
angry okay your mind gets more calm
people can't upset you you don't feel as
jealous uh you don't feel like you need
three pieces of pizza right now okay
your mind your mental afflictions
steadily start to fade all right
but but
it's not because they're gone okay it's
because you feel a little bit calmer and
you cannot stay there it's not possible
to stay there you must come out sooner
or later okay you got to get back in
your car people are going to kick you
out of the church okay you got to get
back in your car then you move quickly
back through all the levels right you go
back oh now I can hear my ears now I can
hear my heart now I can hear my nose
hairs now I can hear the person slurping
next to me and now I can hear the
traffic your mind comes out very quickly
so that kind of meditation is
considered uh not so useful just to get
your mind deeper and quieter and then
come back out without any other object
is considered a mistake right there's no
benefit to it you will have to get back
in your car and drive home and then that
meditation is over and you haven't
gotten anything out of it all
right to
you can go all the way up to the top of
the eight levels of meditation but it
will not stop you from suffering okay
you still have to get in your car and
you still have to go home and you you
still have to get old while you're in
your car okay doesn't stop
anything
K uh then he quotes from a text called
we had it
before means the Praise of those who are
worthy of Praise okay the praise of
those who are worthy of
Praise uh those who practice meditation
without getting into world
view those who are blinded by ignorance
okay they can go to the top of the
formless real okay which is called the
peak of existence it's the peak of
existence young children their suffering
will come back their suffering will come
back C
Dr so their whole meditation practice
has only served to bring them back into
the circle of s
that's that's an ancient scripture about
[Music]
that then Lord Buddha recounted the
story about a yogi who got who got into
trying to get to those higher meditative
without using them for any big
purpose people who don't understand how
things work they can go to High states
of
meditation but they aren't doing
anything to stop their view that Aspen
works all right
they believe that Aspen work they they
have reached high levels of meditation
but they still think that aspin has
something what in it that that takes
away a headache they still believe that
they can meditate they can go to
extremely high levels of meditation but
they still believe there's something
inside an aspirin which can take away a
he right they believe
that they haven't lost their belief in
in a doc okay do means Atman means self
that just means an asp that has
something in it that works there's no
such thing okay do when Buddhists say
there's no self what they mean is an
aspen is not an aspen why there's
nothing in it that works to take away
your headche if if a is a stone in
ASP is a piece of gravel from the
parking lot and as why not
why
not it doesn't take headache it's not
ask people don't go out the parking lot
and pick out a piece of gravel eat it
when they have headache okay it doesn't
have anything in it that takes away
headache
right but Aspen
does which plan
so if you get really good at
meditation but you don't use it to
understand why Aspen works right you
don't apply it to
anything you just go on thinking the way
you did before and you get very very
good at
meditation that's like purposely trying
to screw up your mind that's like
purposely trying to disturb your mind it
will simply disturb your mind
and means it will disturb your stir up
your
mind that's like the story of
the okay there was a meditator in India
called I think he tells the story here
let me
see yeah here it
is y
he got to the highest of the eight form
and formless Realms right called peak of
existence he spent many years on that
meditating on that level and
Ne then uh what he say he didn't have
time to go to a
barber CU he was in meditation all the
time
so he got this really long hair he got
really long hair they call Raa Raa means
dreadlocks his hair started to tie up in
dreadlock but he was actually sort of
proud of it because he said oh people
will think I'm a great meditator if I
have these long UNR dreadlocks then
everybody will be impressed he was happy
then CH cha means a rra so
means started chewing on his what do you
call Bob Marley Bob Marley on his Bob
Marley dreadlocks that he was so proud
of then rat started to he was in deep
meditation and they were cheerwing off
his dread
Liv didn't you know one day he got out
of his meditation he went down to the
stream to get a drink of water looked in
the Stream and his dreadlocks were out
of order you know this side didn't match
this side you know and he got really
upset right he said that people will
laugh at me you know people are supposed
to be impressed by my grand now it's all
off you
know split ends
too there's a story that I don't know if
it's true but they say that that his
anger was so powerful that it sent him
to a hell
room he uh he was so upset but his his
anger created a Bad Karma and when he
died he went
to so the point is not that we simply
get into a more and more relatively
subtle State of Mind okay it's not that
you get to your breath from the car
noises and it's not that you go from
your breath to the heart noises and it's
not that you go from the heart noises to
the ear noises it's not progress
get to a
point get to that one sliver of
meditation stop because the point is not
to meditate more deeply the point is to
use the very silent State of Mind to see
emptiness directly
[Music]
okay if you get to this state of
shamata deep state of shamata you will
get to a point where it feels as
though you could count the atoms in the
wall of the church okay that you could
look at the wall of the church and you
could count the ATS you feel like that
this is a very very difficult
section so in a deep state of
meditation will there even come to you
fleeting images we can say fleeting
images okay of an apple or a piece of a
song
or or similar object okay will a
fleeting image even come to your mind of
some of a of a red color
or they give other examples like
uh a
fleeing sense of wanting something or a
fleeting sense of disliking someone tiny
tiny
fleeting senses of of things and they
say other example would be a a boy or a
girl thinking about a boy or thinking
about a girl a
slight fleeting image crosses your mind
right in a very deep state of
meditation uh you are able to
even hold the Mind back from touching
those images as they fly through your
mind so when images flying through your
mind at the rate of what is it 65 per
second in a in a single second
65 discreet images will pass through
your mind occasionally red occasionally
girl
occasionally I don't like occasionally I
wish I had okay very fleing immediate
images will fly through your mind right
and a yogi at this stage they are able
to just ignore them they they even
consider them
uh what do you call potential problem
they are aware of a 165 of a second's
fleeting thought of a color and they
just they're able in the 65th of a
second to avoid
it so therefore they don't get problems
like jealousy or anger or things like
that and if they do they don't have any
problem
then uh just when you fall asleep okay
like you close your eyes and you fall
off to sleep you automatically go into
deep
meditation you cannot withdraw from your
senses without going into a deep
meditation so these kinds of things are
happening when you have sh
there
are foolish people nowadays we see in
Tibet uh they don't want to spend the
effort and time it takes to go
through the instructions the real
instructions okay they would like some
little you know I did that what do they
call it I remember a meeting at double
day we were having a big meeting at
double day on the 53rd floor of their
building
on just south of Central Park and um
they looked at me you know and I they
said do you have any books in mind you
know what are your next five books and I
said well I want to do one about uh how
to improve science you know physics I
want to write about how to improve
physics and they're like no no I want so
and then
uh and we went to a whole list and then
they said guess what could you do a k c
book you know I said what's a candy book
they said a book you can digest on a
short plane
flight a book you can read the whole
thing through on a short plane flight
that's called a candy book can you write
a candy book and I'm
like he's saying p is
saying there people in Tibet nowadays
they want a candy book they want
somebody to give them a candy
book and it better be talking about
Z
okay I did an examination recently I
taught a plain old long Rim text for a
week and then on two days I taught this
ttic something I was just curious to see
how many people would come to the ttic
one and skip the
[Music]
long so you know give me something
interesting give me some inner body
chak or give me CH chak means chak means
mahamudra you know give me some
mysterious almost incomprehensible
mahamud text you know that will turn me
on you know give me something like that
a candy book about mahamudra
or or inner body okay
so and then people are attracted to that
kind of thing they want something
sensational
he said in in in tiet in modern times
which was what
1921 he said it's very difficult to find
a person who has
sham it's very difficult to find a
person who has
sham as it's described in this text ch
then there's a rude text on mahamud
mahamud is a very high sexy meditation
on meditating on your mind okay the r
text was written by the first is the
first
Ben his Holiness the first p mama
said don't study my M
Tex be careful studying my Maham
why it explains I mean don't study it on
a surface level that text teaches you
how to meditate upon your mind what are
you watching when you when you do
Mamud your own
mind is your mind
emptiness hopefully not
okay can you check can you check the air
they're getting sleepy we got Crank It
Up
uh so you know the purpose of M mud
meditation as Jason just said the
purpose is to see The Emptiness of your
mind the purpose is to see the ult
ultimate nature of your mind okay but
his ho is the first pension Lama said
almost everybody in Tibet who is trying
to study m mudra is focusing on the Mind
itself and not on the nature of the mind
okay so they are focusing on a thing
which is deceptive
illusory they are they are focusing on
something which will hurt them right
they they're looking at the mind with
the wrong part of the mind and he's
complaining about the state of
meditators in Tibet okay they are not
using their meditation for the right
purpose they are focusing the meditation
on the wrong thing even those are trying
to explore the nature of the Mind end up
looking
at just the mind just watching their
thoughts and not trying to explore where
those thoughts came
from those kinds of people think they're
doing great
meditation
uh they are meditating on a what you
called
a ball
of what's bronze bronze not quite
copper bronze what's cheaper than
bronze brass yeah that's it they are
meditating on brass and thinking it's
gold they are meditating on brass and
think it's
[Music]
go l
they are doing more no more
than uh traveling a path which leads to
Nowhere that the spiritual path they
have chosen leads to
know most of them are mistaking subtle
dullness for meditation I would guess
that 90% of the people who are able to
meditate on a regular basis even among
people we know if they're doing it for
more than five or 10 minutes are are
just engaged in subtle dullness okay no
more all of us okay if you're meditating
try to meditate for more five and 10
minutes if you say you're on the object
for an hour or half an
hour very very likely you are in sub
right
[Music]
that's not even a form real meditation
or formless real meditation okay that's
nothing it doesn't subtle dullness
doesn't get you anywhere long protracted
meditations in which you wander or space
out all right they don't even get you to
a higher rer nothing they have no effect
maybe if you meditate on those for a
long time you can set up yourself a
rebirth as a
dog okay no because the state of mind is
similar okay or like a cat right a cat
has great uh attention cats have great
capacity for
attention
focus but but that's
all they they live short violent lives
and then they're finished right there's
no not capable of of like ethical
breakthroughs or something like that
okay they they they eat they kill birds
and then they are killed and that's the
end of their life but they're they're
capable of Greater
[Music]
tension one of the great uh wise men of
said there are fools who meditate on M
they think they are meditating on
the the majority of them are collecting
causes to become born as
animals or else at best they could fall
into a lower Nirvana what's a lower
Nirvana
what's
new you permanently remove negative
states of mind no more anger no more
jealousy no more desire you're not
capable of being upset it's worth it
right nobody can upset you it's not
possible for someone to upset you
that's it's not possible to want to eat
too much uh it's not possible to feel
jealous of your ex partner's boyfriend
or something like that you don't have
the capacity to have those thoughts you
just don't have the capacity what makes
that lower if it's lower what makes it
lower it doesn't help anybody
else it's not serving anybody else it
it's good for you it makes you happy and
your mind is clear and you don't have
any more problems but it doesn't do
anything to help the rest of the world
right that's what makes it a learner
better
at the best mistaken meditation will get
you to a lower Nirvana or a birth in the
formless okay so in M meditation which
is very sexy why it's very it's very
powerful why
as far as the nine levels why is mahab
meditation a good
one yeah you're using the mind to watch
the mind right when you get dness what
do you
do you just watch the dness and then
you're not D
anymore okay you get bright and bushy
tailed towards your dullness You observe
your dullness which makes you
undul so it's it's very
efficient is very efficient and then the
llamas the great llamas like the first
Pion he said don't stop there uh use
that meditation to explore the nature of
your mind you know don't just watch your
mind explore the nature of your mind so
then there were these guys they went
meditation and they reported back to
their
Lama I have seen the nature of the mind
I said what is it he said you know the
mind doesn't have any colors at all and
it also has no shapes you can't say the
mind is square or round or oblong
and you can't say the mind is red or
blue or green I have grasped the nature
of the
mind okay I have they call face to face
right M they say face to face I went
face to face with the mind and I
understood its nature what is it nature
hey it's not
physical is that the nature of the mind
no yes it's it's a nature of okay the
mind's not physical if you meditate on
the mind and you conclude that it's not
polka do you are
correct okay but that's not its ultimate
me you have explored one of the natures
of the mind it's not polka dot right but
but you didn't understand the Deep
nature of the mind okay so you can do
mahamudra
meditation by the way that yoga post
today called mahamudra you take a
retention you stretch out the central
Channel and it was meant to trigger a
perception of the real nature of the
Mind see it is called Mud for a
reason what is the real nature of the
Mind what are you supposed to think
about when you watch the mind and
M
huh yeah that it has something let's
compare it to a meditation on The
Emptiness of your screaming boss or
spouse okay your your boss picking on
you or your spouse picking on you all
right saying bad things about you or to
you okay let's compare the mind to
them
when when you're having a problem and
your spouse or your boss is criticizing
you what's the natural
reaction you you want to yell back
okay what will happen if you yell
back you will plant new season your mind
and then next week you'll see them
yelling again right if you get angry and
yell back at a person who's criticizing
you you only perpetuating that person in
your life okay so let's put it a
different way if someone criticizes you
or yells at you and you had to choose
the one most stupid thing to do what
would it
beell okay next question what is the
single most natural thing for a human
being who's criticized to do criticize
that okay that's why you're a human
being and not an angel already right
that's why you're stuck in this room
already okay
uh if you can't grasp all of the ideas
or or you can't really relate uh closely
to all the nine levels of meditation and
it's difficult for to
grasp uh what's he talking about the
first uh form level and what would that
feel like and what's that list thing and
I mean he's been going on for four or
five days now about all these things you
know if you find it difficult to wrap
your head around you right how is that
similar to a yelling
boss yeah it's coming from you okay uh
meeting a yelling boss and meeting a
mind in your own head which doesn't get
the book completely right it's the same
thing right it's the same thing you
planted seeds in your mind before by
failing to help people who didn't
understand something maybe they were
trying to get to the Paradise Cafe and
you were busy and you said look I don't
have time right now to tell you you
Google it you know you'll find it sooner
or later it's the one nearby and you
take off
right you don't give them understanding
you planted a seed in your mind not to
understand this
book okay you planted a seed in your
mind not to understand the levels of
meditation right meeting meeting lousy
things in your head is the same as
meeting lousy people in your life all
right they both come from seeds in your
mind they're both coming from seas in
your mind so in a mahud meditation in a
real
one you focus on the mind and you think
about where did that thought come from
what was the karma that I collected what
did I do to someone else for me to have
to hear that thought inside my head all
right that's a real mahamud
meditation that's the real nature of
your
mind the stuff that comes up in your
mind good or bad is all also coming from
seeds that you planted before it's the
same as the people you meet at work
right it's not different that's a real
mudo meditation on your own mind right
it's not to look at your mind and say
gee it's not
visible that's true but that's not the
ultimate nature of the money okay got
it you guys feel sleepy to me I don't
know let's keep going
[Music]
yeah so some foolish people said I
meditated on the mind and I figured out
that it's Pol polka dot not po
okay so there was a famous uh there's a
little line in the M scriptures all
right by the first P it's misspelled
here okay it's Rd it looks like R is it
Rd it's supposed to be
SD and both words are uh both words are
uh like one page in a million you never
see this word even spelled correct you
don't see it and they miss all right
so s right
SD just be here
now be here
now
uh don't try to what
don't don't cut the flow of your mind
from from the past your mind is Flowing
from the past right your mind is flowing
into the present from the past don't
don't mess with it don't mess with the
Mind flowing to the present from the
past
and and don't uh anticipate the flow of
the Mind into the future
okay don't mess with the Mind flowing
from the past don't try to anticipate
where the mind is going going to go now
next all right he that's a
mahamudra saying that means be in the
present moment don't F around with what
your mind was doing yesterday and don't
worry about where your mind's going to
be tomorrow stay in the present moment
of the mind that was a a famous M mudra
St statement with that be
useful is it
ultimate no I mean you'd have to stay in
the present moment and examine the
nature of your mind as we just described
it you would have to examine the mind in
the present moment but think you know
what did I do last week to make my mind
sound like this right now right that's a
weird meditation
right because you're divorcing yourself
from the mind you're watching the mind
and saying who made it like that
what's the Mind thinking at that
moment you're watching your mind think
some weird thing right like your mind is
distracted during meditation and it
upsets you and you're watching your mind
and you're saying why am I always
distracted all right who made your mind
distracted but when you're looking at it
and thinking about who made it
distracted are you distracted
not anymore you can say not anymore you
said said like
that so anyway his point is the first
ping llama in his M text he says stick
to the present moment stick to the mind
of the present moment don't worry about
what was happening before don't worry
about what's going to come stick to the
mind in the present moment but it means
examine the nature of the Mind in the
present moment it doesn't mean just
space out in the present moment
okay there are me there are people who
thought oh I'm going to do M meditation
and they thought oh I'm going to stay in
the present
moment that meditation accomplished
nothing more than to waste their life
the attempt to stay in the present
moment accomplish nothing more than to
waste all the moments of their life he's
making a joke get it okay the attempt to
stay in the present moment without
examining what's going on in the present
moment where why your mind is thinking
that in the present moment just to watch
your mind to stay in the present moment
is to waste all the moments of your life
because it doesn't take you anywhere
it won't take you to any spiritual
pattern
level we'll go a few more minutes and
then we'll take a small break
if you want to make your meditation into
a spiritual practice right if you want
your practice of meditation to take you
somewhere in this
L then join to that meditation some high
ideal okay join some high ideal to that
meditation he gives three examples okay
he gives three examples one is ch
CH means body
means I would like to be the one who
turns this world on and makes people
understand where things are coming from
and then ends poverty Etc in this world
I would like to be the
world I would like to save this world
and you can do you can really do
honestly you you individually can do
it
nun I'm tired of seeing people suffer in
my life I'm tired of it how much do you
have to see before you do something how
many people have to die in your life
before you do
something how many people do you have
how many big people do you have to see
fall and how many small people do you
have to see get cancer and just die and
how many good friends do you have to see
go through aging right and forgetfulness
and the the gradual Corruption of the
body you know how many do you have to
see before you before you want to try to
do
something or join your meditation to an
examination of where things are really
coming
from why is my mind distracted today I
heard somebody last like
that
Rion or at least try to seek some higher
what do you call it protection
in your life at least try to seek some
kind of protection in your
life please can't help you when you get
cancer neither can
doctors okay nobody can help you when
you get old right as you get old as you
go through the process of Aging no one
can help you there's no protection try
to find some real protection
if you do if you take your meditation
practice right you're trying to work to
the nine levels you're trying to apply
the eight antidotes to the five problems
as you do so do it with a motivation of
wanting to help the world then that
meditation becomes a higher practice
right so what he's saying is that he's
complaining what do you call it he's
attacking meditation for meditation sake
he's attacking meditation for meditation
sake
meditation is a tool that has no benefit
in and of itself okay join it with a
wish to save the world it becomes the
highest spiritual
practice join it with
an join it with a concern for the pain
of the world and it becomes a cost for
Nirvana join your
meditation
with okay I got a tie two of them
together your meditation will bring you
to Nirvana if you do it with an
appreciation for people's pain and the
correct understanding of where things
are coming from n may
choose if you meditate with the thought
that there might be something there that
can protect you and other people then it
becomes D okay it becomes a spiritual
practice but but meditation for the sake
of meditation meditation for the sake of
watching your breath or something like
that meditation for the purpose of just
getting a Calm Mind these are
not it's not a reason to
meditate there were two mistakes in
ancient about mahamudra okay the
practice of
meditating on the mind can be done
mistakenly in two different ways okay so
if you're interested in doing it mingly
I'll give do two different wayes okay
one is called
cellone
cellone Sone is some weird practice
where
uh is this a
clock
uh now think of everything in the world
that's not the clock okay everything on
this planet which is not this clock just
get it in your head tell me when you're
ready
roughly ready okay this clock everything
except this clock okay got it in your
mind now think of everything which is
the opposite of those
things that's a
c okay now when you receive a clock your
mind is doing something similar to that
okay that's one way of
looking at how your mind sees a clock
your mind sees a clock by eliminating
other
possibilities is it a
banana no is it a football
field no is it President Obama's left
ear no and then you keep going and then
and finally you say well then it must be
a clock cuz that's the only thing left
all right that you're actually your mind
does that to some extent your mind
perceives objects by canceling what the
object is not your your mind perceives
objects by canceling what the object is
not but that's not really emptiness okay
people Mook that for
emptiness okay people thought that was
emptiness
you will hear hundreds of weird versions
of What Emptiness is the test of whether
they are
weird is do they help anybody all right
it doesn't really help anybody to say
the clock is the opposite of everything
that's not the
clock it's true but it's not
emptiness is it a
negation yeah isn't an negation of of
something that doesn't EX
exist is it refusing something which
doesn't
exist no so it's not emptiness it's just
an interesting fact all right that's
not
means uh try to meditate without what do
you call you hear people say that you
buy a new age tape from I don't know
sounds great or
something
right SS
true and uh
you know the guy gets on the tap and
says just let the thoughts run to your
mind and don't think about anything let
them float through your mind and then
the worst thing they say don't attach to
it and then I I keep asking them what do
you mean don't attach to it they say
don't don't own it no don't own the
thought let the thought go through your
mind that's called z z it has no
practical benefit at
all those kinds of meditation will do
nothing
to they will do nothing to stop to help
stop your misunderstanding of the world
they won't help
okay what do I mean you have to stop
your misunderstanding of the world what
do I mean in the sense of your
boss but how does the wrong how does a
misunderstanding of your boss perpetuate
your
suffering yeah you yell back
okay if you don't realize that the boss
is coming from yelling at people then
you will yell back and then that
misunderstanding will bring the boss
back next week you see that's Sun that's
a cycle you you get yelled at you yell
back you get yelled at you yell back
okay thinking that the clock is
everything is the opposite of what's not
the clock or trying to look at your
thoughts in your mind and not attach
them they don't do anything to help you
with your
boss you see they have no effect on on
your boss you can think them but it it
doesn't help you with the real problems
of life
okay so they're worthless those are
[Music]
worthless people you know people don't
know me very well they bring me a book
from bars and Nobles they bring me the
latest I don't know book about not
attaching to your thoughts from bar and
no you know and I'm like thank you very
much you know I really appreciate it
then I go home and I just sometimes I
throw it out the window of the car on
the way
home okay doesn't do
me the best you can do with those kinds
of lousy meditations are that you will
end up like the guy with the
dreadlocks that's the best that can
happen okay what to
him okay that's the best all right
uh oh cool one more line and we'll get
to emptiness ready we will take a break
okay uh no I mean we'll finish the line
we'll take a break and then we can start
on emptiness
y because now you know how to meditate
perfectly
the problem with practice text is that
it takes like a day to teach it and then
it takes like 20 years to okay
anyway
uh don't get attracted to to worthless
paths don't get attracted to worthless
paths don't get attracted to some
some worthless new AG thing that tells
you you know watch the thoughts flow
through your mind like clouds and don't
don't what don't don't relate to them or
something doesn't help with your B the
test of a Viewpoint is will it help you
with your boss or your spouse right
okay
girl this is beautiful okay it's not
being
sectarian to learn to distinguish
between a path which will benefit you
and a path which will not you know it's
not being sectarian to say uh you know I
respect your I respect your book I
respect your work I respect that you
want to help people uh I'm sure that it
has some benefit for you right but then
uh if if you're dealing with a few years
of help right a normal human being it
takes 20 as your parents know it takes
20 years to eject someone from the home
you know I mean they they are not
they're no use to anybody for 20 years
right and then uh the last 20 years of
life are are are bust right you're too
old to think straight you're looking for
your car keys all the
time I
uh you know an older person out the
other day I said let's go to lunch I was
trying to cheer them up you know let's
go to lunch you know they said yeah yeah
let's go to lunch you know
so we got the car you know we got the
car we we we went out of the driveway we
hit the Thomas Road right and then she
said I have to go to the
bathroom I'm like the restaurant's only
like 10 minutes I got to go
now and I'm like I I I turn off at a
coffee shop you know okay let's rush in
you know I mean how much you can Rush at
that age
but so you know we we couldn't wait we
couldn't drive to the restaurant we
laugh but that's us right the last 20
years of our life we're just too tired
uh to do anything the first 20 years are
you're too dumb to do anything okay so
that leaves like about 40 I'm sorry 20
useful years in between
okay you got about 20 years to do what
whatever you're going to do in your life
you got to do it in the middle because
the and then there's this joking to B
you know you're going to sleep half of
those 20 years you know so cut it to 10
years you know you have 10 years of of
intelligent life in you right you have
10 years of energy and
intelligence to play with you don't have
time to read new age books about not
thinking about the thoughts as they
float to your head it's not that those
people are evil okay and it's not that
we should burn them at this
St but
uh
but but uh I'm just
kidding but it's a it's a waste of
Irreplaceable precious moments of your
life of your of the of the age of your
life when you are clear thinking and you
got out of the house you know you have
10 15 years of real life to live are you
going to spend a month of it on some
book that's about don't think about your
thoughts concentrate on not thinking
about your
thoughts you know you don't have time
you know you don't have
time try to
develop the
capacity to
uh to detect
flop all right try to develop the
capacity to detect flu and if it's fluff
then leave it for later you know if I
live to 80 I I'll read your book you
know okay while your mind is strong
you're not too old yet you have time you
can meditate you know you're not a crazy
teenager uh those that those years of
your life reserve them for something of
substance okay
the other thing they always say at
double day they say anything you write
will publish gu anything I say why they
said content content content you know
they're like you got content and there's
it's not fluff you have real content you
know and so look for things of substance
and look for things which can really
help you in your life and don't don't
waste your time learn to distinguish
between fluff and nonf fluff all right
cool especially with your meditation the
the time spent in the core of your mind
is precious and the core of your mind is
very fragile and the core of your mind
is very vulnerable and you have to
reserve uh the highest teachings when
you get close to the core of your mind
in
meditation uh you want to have something
powerful and substantial to use when you
get there okay you don't want fluff
around the core of your mind mind if you
work hard to get close to the core of
your mind you better have something cool
you can do with it and don't just bring
some garbage to the core of your mind
okay all right bring something life
saving and Planet changing to the core
of your mind right